Finding Aid for Julia Makarem papers, 1930-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Julia Makarem papers 1930-2006, 1987-2002
Makarem, Julia.
1 oversize folders
5 linear feet
0258 Aa 2; UAm
American born Druze, active in the American Druze Society and concerned with the history of the Druze in the United States. Papers relate to American Druze Society activities and to history of Druze in America.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Julia Mullin Makarem (donor number 9184 ) in 2002. Additional material has been received.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Julia Mullin Makarem, an American born Druze who devoted her life to her people and her Druze faith, was born in Detroit, Michigan. As a child, she witnessed the formation of the American Druze Society through the work of Druze immigrants including her parents, Farris Mullin (Melhim) and Nagela Farris Mullin, ne Abu Shakra.
In 1962 she met and married Sami Nassib Makarem, a graduate student at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. She worked at Comerica Bank until her first child was born. Together they had four children, two daughters, Sahar and Rand, and twin sons, Samir and Nassib. In 1962 she was elected National President of the American Druze Society and moved with her husband to Ann Arbor. In May of 1962, Sami received his Ph.D.
In 1963, Sami and Julia moved with their first child, Sahar, to Lebanon. They lived in the mountain village, Aytat, and in Beirut. There she participated in and contributed to many community activities in the fields of education, social work and welfare, especially during the years of war. She also served as President of the American University of Beirut Women's Association between 1974-1977. Then in 1987, the Makarem family moved back to Dearborn, Michigan. In 1992 she was elected as a National Board Director of the American Druze Society serving until 1998. She was National President of the organization serving from July 4, 1997 until July 3, 1999.
Makarem also served as a teacher and instructor. She taught at Lebanon's American University of Beirut, St. Joseph University, The Harriri Foundation, a Saudi Arabian Philanthropic Academic Program and at Polyglot, a British School. She was the Georgetown University, Washington, DC advisor to the Georgetown Junior Year Abroad Program at the American University of Beirut. She has also taught in various schools in America such as Webber Middle School in Detroit and Fordson High School in Dearborn, Michigan as well as at Baker College. She taught both secondary schools as part of a "Business Education Partnership" for Comerica Bank.
The Julia Mullin Makarem papers are divided into four series: Personal, American Druze Society, Publications, and Audio/Visual Material.
Subjects:
Makarem, Julia.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Druzes--United States.; American Druze Society.; Center for Arab American Studies collections.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Makarem, Julia.; American Druze Society.; Druzes--United States.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Center for Arab American Studies collections.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Motion pictures.
- Personal
  The Personal series consists of information on Julia Makarem, her husband, Sami Nassib Makarem, her father-in-law's calligraphy work, and her uncle, a political and tribal leader of the Druze in Lebanon. Included are articles about Sami Makarem from "Our Heritage" and biographical information for Julia Makarem.
  - Julia Mullin Makarem
    - Autobiographical Essays (Box 1)
    - Autobiography 2007 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, etc. (Box 1)
    - Biographical sketch and personal clippings (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Essays, Michigan State University files (Box 1)
    - Druze Society articles (Box 1)
    - Druze Information and History (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - Sami Nassib Makarem: article 1985 (Box 1)
  - Sheikh Nassib Makarem: sample of calligraphy 1986 (article in Arabic) (Box 1)
  - Uncle: Arabic article (Box 1)
- American Druze Society
  The American Druze Society series contains general information on the American Druze Foundation, including controversies and issues during Julia Makarem's presidency of the organization 1997-1999. Many of the files relate to the charitable activities of the Society.
  - American Druze Foundation 1991-2000 (Box 1)
    (religious background, pamphlets, miscellaneous)
  - Annual Meeting 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors 1991-1999, 4 folders (Box 1)
    (missing 1994 transcripts of meetings included with 1999)
  - Chapters (non-Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Charities
    - Correspondence 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Foundation of Social Welfare 1983-1999 (Box 1)
      (English and Arabic correspondence)
    - Health Establishment of Druze Community (pamphlets) 1996 (Box 1)
    - IMAN Hospital
      - 1997-1999 (Box 1)
        (English correspondence, pamphlet)
      - Arabic Letters (Box 1)
    - Orphanage
      - Pamphlets (background) 1984, 1995 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1994, 1998 (Box 1)
      - Tuition Program (correspondence, newsletters) 1994-1997 (Box 1)
    - Salamar Foundation for Social Development
      - Pamphlets (background) 1998 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1998-1999 (Box 1)
      - Le Bulletin de L'ESCO 1998 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, By-laws and Commandments 1987-1995 (Box 1)
    (constitution and By-laws, legal advise, community benefits, ethical commandments, and five principles)
  - Conventions
    - Programs and Invitations 1947-2002 scattered dates, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Convention Roundup 1998, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Statistics and Information 1997-1998 (Box 2)
      (interest in conventions chart, information about conventions)
    - Lecture: Social Image of the Druze Woman 1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Arabic (Box 2)
    - General 1988-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (correspondence to, from, and about Julia Makarem)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Cultural Center (Box 2)
    (pamphlets, copy of general information of services)
  - Directory of Paid Members 1995-1996, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - "Druze religious jurisprudence and personal status law" edited by Julia Makarem 1996, include computer disks (Box 2)
    (translated in English by Salman Falah -- The Civil Status Laws of the Druze Unifiers. Druzes Sect Vital Statistics Ordinance issued in Lebanon on February 24, 1948 and amended on July 2, 1959. Introduction signed by Sagacity Sheikh of Druzes, Hussein Jarbouth)
  - Funds (correspondence, receipts, reports) 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Immigration Case (correspondence, an outline of events) 1998 (Box 2)
  - IRS Case 1997-1999, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Legal matters (various), 3 folders (Box 2)
    (include Ruth Simons v Sami Merhi)
  - Mailings (flyers, fundraising letters, updates) 2003-2006 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Chapter ADS (membership log 2000 activities) (Box 2)
  - Michigan Chapter Ladies Auxiliary Meeting Minutes 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Chapter miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - National Organization Presidential Election 2006 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Our Heritage (information about newsletter, Arabic writing), undated (Box 3)
    - Young Druze Professionals Newsletter (newsletters, information on the Shadawi Club) 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - People
    - Baheej Abou-Alhosn (Box 3)
    - Ali Y Assaf (correspondence) 1997-1999 (Box 3)
    - Fouad Chafic Barakat (correspondence) 1994, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Mr. Abdulhamid Boukhzam (biographical sketch) (Box 3)
    - Mohamed Khodar Halabi, M.D. (article from Our Heritage), undated (Box 3)
    - Mark Hamdan (resume) 1992 (Box 3)
    - Dr. Raymond Hamden (biographical sketch) (Box 3)
    - Sarah Howell, University of Michigan Ph.D. candidate, "Looking for Home in the Global Disorder" (Box 3)
    - Casey Kasem 1995, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
      (photographs, pamphlet-Man of the Year Dinner, correspondence)
    - Nafe Katter 1979-1992 (scattered) (Box 3)
      (photograph, biographic sketch, correspondence)
    - Chibli El Masri (letter of recommendation) 1998 (Box 3)
    - Fouad Sleem 1994, 1997-1998, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - 1992-1998 (scattered) (Box 3)
      (various ADS activities, Individuals-Jamiil Salman, Ali Amen, Widad Salman, Yusuf Bomorra, Hissan Bomorra Yusuf, Julia Makarem, Sami Makarem)
    - Photograph of Julia Makarem, Casey Kasem, Munir Kasem 1994 (Folder 1)
      (located in UAm)
    - Group portraits of Druze conventions and other gatherings 1930-1946 (scattered) (Folder 1)
    - Joseph Bomorra, businessman undated (Box 3)
  - Presidential Reports 1996-1999 (Box 3)
  - President's file 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Realia, buttons (Box 3)
  - Yearbook articles 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Yearbook correspondence 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Yearbooks 1980, 1990-2006 (Box 3)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes national and state Druze newsletters and periodicals.
  - Our Heritage, 1980-1987 (Box 3)
  - Our Heritage, 1988-2006 (Box 4)
  - The Heritage (Box 4)
  - ADS Southern California Chapter Newsletter 1991, 1998 (Box 4)
  - AUB Bulletin and other American University of Beirut publications 1980s-2002 (Box 4)
  - DOCO Newsletter 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - ADS Michigan Chapter Newsletter-Al-Risalah 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - The Arabic Progress (Nahdat Al-Arab) (Folder 1)
    - First Mihrajan of Al-Bayan 1947 (in English and Arabic) (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Articles (Folder 1)
    - St. George Syrian Orthodox Church 25th Anniversary 1947 (Box 4)
    - Serials (in Arabic) (Box 4)
  - Al-Mithaq (in Arabic) (Box 5)
- Audio Visual Recordings
  The Audio/Visual series include 8mm films and audiocassette tapes. They contain images and recordings of American Druze Society conventions, meetings, and picnics.
  - Sound cassettes
    - American Druze Society "Bs meets" July 1, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting January 10, 1998, 3 audiocassettes (Box 5)
    - Conference Call: Board, For my letter to Faouzi Mokarem (Box 5)
    - S.H.A.D.A.W.I. Club 1996 (Box 5)
  - Motion pictures, 8 mm
    - Aunt Helen's Williamsburg Picnic, Convention 1969, 4 rolls (Box 5)
    - Detroit Convention 1966 and Washington, D.C. Convention, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Picnics July 4, 1962, 1964 and Flushing Picnic, July 4, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Picnic July 4, 1965, 2 rolls (Box 5)
    - Flint Convention 1961 Helen Dow (Box 5)
    - Florida 1960s (Box 5)
    - Unknown Convention and Aunt Najila 1960s (Box 5)
    - Sahar, Rand, Julie September 1965 first half (Box 5)